Frank L. Engel

Geographer

11222 Candle Park San Antonio, TX 78249



+1 210-868-5788



http://https/www.usgs.gov/staffprofiles/frank-l-engel





San Antonio, TX 78249

Geographer and researcher with 6+ years of experience in developing new tools, technology, and apps using remote sensing to solve real-world problems. Very familiar with standard software design practices, operational deployment of technology and hardware, and providing practical training. Passionate about good project management and clear communication through scientific publications, documentation, and other media.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

U.S. Geological Survey – Water Mission Area Hydrologic Remote **Sensing Branch**

EDGE Geographer | 40 hours/week | GS 13

Geographer | 40 hours/week | GS 12

(Jun 2017 - Dec 2021) U.S. Geological Survey – Oklahoma-Texas Water Science Center

U.S. Geological Survey - Illinois Water Science Center

Geographer 40 hours/week GS 12	(Jun 2015 - Jun 2
Geographer 40 hours/week GS 11 (Mar 2014 - Jun 2015)	(Mar 2014 - Jun 2
Geographer 40 hours/week GS 7	(Apr 2013 - Mar 2
Hydrologist-Student Trainee 20-30 hours/week GS 5	(Apr 2012 - Apr 2

EDUCATION

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

PhD in Geography (Civil & Env Engineering Minor)

(Sep 2007 - May 2014)

Texas State University-San Marcos MS in Geography

3.88 GPA (Sep 2005 - Dec 2007)

(Jan 2022 – Present)

2017) 2015) 2014) 2013)

3.92 GPA

3.34 GPA

Texas State University-San Marcos

BS in Physical Geography (Music Minor)

(Sep 1999 - May 2005)

SELECT PUBLICATIONS

Fulton, J.W., Engel, F.L., Eggleston, and Chiu, C.-L., in review, Computing river discharge using the probability concept algorithm: U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods 3-A26.

Duan, J.G., Cadogan, A., and Engel, F.L., in review, Flow discharge estimation using video recording from smallunoccupied aircraft systems. Journal of Hydraulic Engineering.

Despax, A., Le Coz, J., Hauet, A., Mueller, D. S., Engel, F. L., Blanquart, B., Renard, B., and Oberg, K.A., 2019, Decomposition of uncertainty sources in acoustic Doppler current profiler streamflow measurements using repeated measures experiments. Water Resources Research, 55, 7520-7540. https://doi.org/10.1029/2019WR025296.

Engel, F.L., Jackson, P.R., and Murphy, E.A., 2018, Flow hydraulics and mixing characteristics in and downstream of Brandon Road Lock, Joliet, Illinois: U.S. Geological Survey Scientific Investigations Report, https://doi.org/10.3133/sir20185094.

Davis, J.J., Jackson, P.R., Engel, F.L., LeRoy, J.Z., Neeley, R.N., Finney, S.T., Murphy, E.A., 2016, Entrainment, retention, and transport of freely swimming fish in junction gaps between commercial barges operating on the Illinois Waterway, Journal of Great Lakes Research. 42(4), 837-848, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jglr.2016.05.005.

SELECT DATA PRODUCTS

Prater, C.D., LeRoy, J.Z., **Engel, F.L.**, Johnson, K.K., 2021, Discharge measurements at USGS streamgage 05536890 Chicago Sanitary and Ship Canal near Lemont, Illinois, 2005-2013: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/F7X63K41.

Engel, F.L., Hartmann, C.A., Petri, B.L., Bryan, P.W., Ockerman, D.J., and Schnoebelen, D.J., 2020, Oceanographic Observations Made Near South Padre Island, Texas, as Part of the South Padre Island Beach Replenishment Study, August 2018–February 2019: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/P9HDIZOC.

Engel, F.L., Fulton, J.W., Lane, J.W., Eggleston, Corbett, S.C., Kohn, M.S., Pulli, J.J., J.R., Adams, J.D., Burton, T.A., Nicotra, M.S., Stephens, V.C., and Dawson, C.D., 2020, Near-field Remote Sensing of River Velocity, Bathymetry, Floodplain Topography, and Discharge at the Arkansas River at Parkdale, Colorado, USA, March 2018: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/F7VTIRDH.

Keele, J.D., and **Engel, F.L.**, 2020, Videos collected for Image Velocimetry at Boneyard Creek at Urbana, IL from 2017 to 2018: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/P9VZ6VYM.

SELECT SOFTWARE APPLICATIONS

- **Engel, F.L.**, in review, Surface Velocity Toolbox (SurfVelTool): U.S. Geological Survey Software Release.

 A graphical user interface and modules used to provide users with a method of computing water velocity profile metadata used in the computation of streamflow with non-contact radars and cameras. Written in Python and Qt.
- **Engel, F.L.**, in development, Image Velocimetry (IVy) Framework: U.S. Geological Survey Software Release.

 A graphical user interface and modules for computing water velocity and streamflow from videos collect by handheld cameras, fixed-mounted cameras, drones, or satellites. IVy Framework includes all image processing and data analysis processes needed for end users to product qualified streamflow measurements in the field. Written in Python and Ot.
- **Engel, F.L.**, in review, CameraDCP: U.S. Geological Survey Software Release.

 A python module and custom operating system application which can be installed on a Raspberry Pi single-board computer used to manage, collect, and upload (via cell telemetry) imagery from connected cameras. Written in Python and bash.

SKILLS

Project Management Image Velocimetry Computer Vision Unoccupied Aerial Systems Remote Sensing

Hydraulics and Turbulence Geographic Information Systems Hydroacoustics AGILE Product Owner

Sediment Transport Geomorphology Uncertainty Analysis

REFERENCES

Doug Schnoebelen OTWSC South Texas Branch, Chief +1 210-460-8899 dschnoebelen@usgs.gov Daniel Pearson NWIS Modernization Program Coordinator +1 512-517-6545 dpearson@usgs.gov

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

Molly Wood Hydrologic Networks Branch, Chief +1 208-850-9929 mswood@usgs.gov

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES